<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvord to Dr. VVomocke. Or, A short reply to his pretended resolution of Mr. Croftons position concerning ministers use of an imposed liturgie. To which is annexed, a blow at Jerubbaal redivivus: discovering his weakness and errours in defence of his groundless secession from solemn publick worship ministred by the English liturgie. By R.S. the publisher of reformation not separation.</title>
            <author>R. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58672</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S140A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219070</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830601</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830601</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35054</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58672)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35054)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2077:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvord to Dr. VVomocke. Or, A short reply to his pretended resolution of Mr. Croftons position concerning ministers use of an imposed liturgie. To which is annexed, a blow at Jerubbaal redivivus: discovering his weakness and errours in defence of his groundless secession from solemn publick worship ministred by the English liturgie. By R.S. the publisher of reformation not separation.</title>
                  <author>R. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Womock, Laurence. Aron-bimnucha, or, An antidote to cure the Calamites of their trembling for fear of the Ark.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Worcester College Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685. --  Aron-bimnucha, or, An antidote to cure the Calamites of their trembling for fear of the Ark --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>T. P. --  Jerub-baal redivivus, or An essay towards a clear resolution of five seasonable queries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35054:1"/>
            <p>A VVORD TO Dr. VVomocke.</p>
            <p>OR, A ſhort <hi>Reply</hi> to his pretended <hi>Reſolution</hi> of Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Poſition, concerning Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Uſe of an <hi>Impoſed Liturgie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is annexed, A Blow at <hi>Jerubbaal Redivivus:</hi> Diſcovering his <hi>Weakneſs</hi> and <hi>Errours</hi> in Defence of his <hi>Groundleſs Seceſſion</hi> from <hi>Solemn Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> Miniſtred by the <hi>Engliſh Liturgie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>R. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Publiſher of <hi>Reformation not Separation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35054:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Once more trouble thee, and the world, with a few Lines on this unpleaſing ſubject; I would intreat thy pains to read them. Though many ſleight this controverſie, it's of weight: Many <hi>miniſter not</hi> by the Liturgie; they muſt be juſtified, or condemned; publick Worſhip is <hi>confined to Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgical miniſtration;</hi> it muſt be attended, or avoided; and Conſcience muſt direct which is to be done. Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> hath (before, and ſince his impriſonment, in zeal and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs) pointed out the <hi>medium</hi> between <hi>ſinfull miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>groundleſs non-communion;</hi> in both which, he is oppoſed by enemies, calumniated by the wicked, and cenſured by the weak, yea, by Brethren in the Miniſtry, who have never vouchſafed to read what he hath written, nor have once reproved in him any errour. The advantage and increaſe of Separation is ſo viſible, that I may well ſtir up zeal to rebuke and repel it; I have therefore once and again appeared its Antagoniſt: The Blow I now ſtrike is indeed below me; the Aſſault againſt my laſt is very weak. I have written, and pray thee to read, that thou mayeſt not be deceived with great words, which ſignifie nothing; and ſerve to no end, ſave to fit the weak and ſimple to ſpeak evil of the things they do not underſtand. That thou mighteſt do in <hi>judgment and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> what thou art like to be compelled to do by <hi>force</hi> and <hi>fear,</hi> hath been, and yet is the Endeavour and Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, ſeeking purity of Worſhip, in union with the Church, whileſt
R. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="reply">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35054:2"/>
            <head>A Word to Dr. WOMOCKE, By way of Reply to his pretended Reſolve of <hi>Mr. Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton's</hi> Poſition concerning Liturgies: And a Blow at <hi>Jerubbaal Redivivus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SInce my publication of <hi>Jerubbaal juſtified,</hi> there hath appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lawrence Womocke,</hi> Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con of <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk. T. P.</hi> alias <hi>D.</hi> Author of <hi>Jerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baal.</hi>
               </note> againſt it, and me, and Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> concerned in it, a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſault, by two different Antagoniſts, as directly contrary each to other, as the Right and Left Wing; onely combined in one <hi>Battalia</hi> under the Prince of Darkneſs, to darken, and, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, deſtroy the truth; ſo that as <hi>Luther</hi> between <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt,</hi> ſtands Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> between a <hi>Prelatical Clergie</hi> and <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts:</hi> yet <hi>vincet veritas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such is the unſpeakable weakneſs of both theſe mens batteries, that I have paſſed them with ſcorn, and ſtood ſtill, in expectation of the on-ſet of their main <hi>Battalia,</hi> on the one ſide, or on the other; but none appearing, I thought good to check their inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation (with which I hear they are puffed up) by theſe few Lines. And firſt, to begin with the Learned Doctor, I would crave leave to tell him, if he will give good aſſurance, that he will in the Schools of the Univerſity give Mr. <hi>Crofton (viva voce)</hi> the Anſwer publiſhed in his name; I will be bound Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſhall meet him to receive it; and if the Boys do not hiſs the Doctor, he ſhall go out Victor. Shall I preſume to take a turn with this reverend Arch-deacon? I muſt then tell him;</p>
            <p>If he did not miſtake, his Printer hath wronged him at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antidote,</hi> p 106. p. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> of his undertaking, to make him read <hi>Non-conformiſt</hi> inſtead of <hi>Now-conformiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Pride, and over weening conceit of our own worth, maketh men Non conformiſts,</hi> I deny; for it is <hi>humility,</hi> and the <hi>fear of the Lord:</hi> they dare not deviate from Divine Directions; and your inſtance is an evidence of the ſame; whilſt Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> doth humbly conſult, whether his <hi>conformity</hi> may conſiſt with his <hi>Miniſterial Office;</hi> and modeſtly offer his Notions to Argumentation; the one ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his <hi>fear of Sin,</hi> whilſt the other ſheweth his <hi>willingneſs to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced,</hi> and both his <hi>humility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:35054:3"/>
His Poſition you have truly tranſcribed, and obſerved the ſtate thereof; but if to affirm, <hi>It cannot be denied to be a moſt baſe and ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh ſervility to proſtitute the Office to which we are apted and ordained</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 107.</note> by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>unto the pleaſure and preſcriptions of men, though the beſt for Quality and Authority,</hi> be to be proud, I will be <hi>proud,</hi> and glory in my pride: And I doubt not, if you were ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendered as a man who ſhould deny this Poſition, you, Sir, would be found proud enough to declare your diſpleaſure, as unjuſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached: I therefore ſoberly require you, to deny it, if you can, or dare; and if you cannot, what meaneth this digreſſive flouriſh?</p>
            <p>Your flouriſh hath indeed given you the <hi>ſtart,</hi> ſo that you have loſt your queſtion, and fall on a <hi>Magiſterial Swada</hi> of Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> conformity: Which of Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Syllogiſms do you here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhake? <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Is not this fair diſputing? But we will weigh your Reaſon. You ſay, <hi>Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>may pleaſe to be ſo humble, as to condeſcend to ſuch an Impoſition for peace and order ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How! condeſcend to <hi>ſuch an Impoſition</hi> which <hi>proſtituteth the Office received from Chriſt to the pleaſure of men?</hi> Can you deſire it? Were you in earneſt when you wrote this? Can you judge it an act of Humility, or not rather the greateſt Arrogancy, for Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to write a <hi>Miniſter of men?</hi> You need good Arguments; for you ſay you will prove it, and that by this Argument.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>What I may lawfully be determined to by my own private judgment, that I may lawfully be determined to by the judgment of Superiors:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But, to ſtated Forms for the celebration of Gods publick Worſhip, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed (and for the very words, terms, and expreſſions) digeſted into method, I may be lawfully determined by my own private judgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ergo, <hi>To ſtated Forms for celebration of Gods ſolemn publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, compoſed, and for the very words, terms, and expreſſions, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted into method, I may lawfully be determined by the judgment of my Superiors.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>But how now, Mr. Doctor? what is become of your Queſtion? Do you not uſe to bring that into your Concluſion? That Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ought to condeſcend to <hi>ſuch an impoſition</hi> which <hi>proſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Office received from Chriſt to the pleaſure of men,</hi> was that you pretended to prove; doth not your Syllogiſm want a foot more to make it reach? But to play with the Prevaricator, know, Sir, I deny both the Propoſitions of your well-formed Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:35054:3"/>
The <hi>Major</hi> you expect to be denied, and therefore enforce; but I alſo deny your <hi>Minor</hi> Propoſition <hi>(viz) That to ſtated Forms for celebration of Gods ſolemn publick Worſhip, compoſed (and for the very words, terms, and expreſſions) digeſted into method, I may lawfully be determined by mine own private judgment.</hi> For, althoogh Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> doth not <hi>exclude his own judgment, when he pleads for the liberty of his own invention, to compoſe and modifie his Forms of publick Worſhip;</hi> yet he <hi>denieth his judgment a power to determine a ſtated form,</hi> ſemper eadem, <hi>always the ſame, for words, terms, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions,</hi> what ever be the variations of Gods providence, and the Churches condition. Nor doth this any way follow on the uſe of his judgment in managing his liberty: That a man may judge a Crutch fit for his now condition, will not conclude, that he may <hi>ſana mente</hi> confine himſelf to a Crutch, one and the ſame Crutch, at all times, in all conditions; this Argumentation is a manifeſt halting before a Creeple: In the laſt, the judgment muſt needs be erroneous, to be corrected before it be obeyed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> you expecting to be denied, do thus enforce.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>What I may lawfully be determined to by a weaker judgment, to that I may be lawfully determined by a judgment that is ſtronger.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But, To ſtated Forms,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I may lawfully be determined by a weaker judgment,</hi> (viz.) <hi>mine own;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ergo, <hi>To ſtated Forms,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I may lawfully he determined by a judgment that was ſtronger,</hi> (viz.) <hi>my Superiors.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Here, Sir, to make the Auditors laugh, I will again become <hi>ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous,</hi> in your fancie, and deny both your Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>I deny the <hi>Major</hi> in the ſequel, <hi>I may be determined by the weaker judgment;</hi> and it will not thence follow, that <hi>I muſt therefore be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the ſtronger judgment:</hi> For Sir, the weaker judgment is <hi>mine own judgment;</hi> and mine own eye is the beſt guide of mine own ſteps, though I ſee but darkly; mine own underſtanding is <hi>my can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle from the Lord;</hi> my dim light <hi>judicium rationale,</hi> ſhineth bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the cloſet of mine own breaſt, than 400. candles, or the <hi>fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renſe judicium</hi> of a Convocation. Sir, the Learned <hi>Davenant</hi> hath taught me, Men may guide us <hi>Judicio Miniſteriali;</hi> but every one muſt judge <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Judicio private, &amp; practicae diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretionis:</hi> Yea, as if to your queſtion, he hath concluded, <hi>Adnu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam praeſcriptionem, aut determinationem alterius, ſine lumine privati judicii, nemo eſt qui credere poteſt, etiamſi cupiat maxime.</hi> And, Sir, I am not bound to impoſſibilities; laugh while you liſt, I will
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35054:4"/>
move by mine own eye, be it never ſo weak, and my Superiors never ſo ſtrong; though my dim light ſeeth not more, it ſeeth more truly and more directively then their brighter.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, that you may know a <hi>man of intolerable pride,</hi> in your account, I deny your <hi>Minor;</hi> and tell you in general, That <hi>the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate judgment of a ſingle perſon may be ſtronger then the judgment of a Convocation, or whole Councel.</hi> Have you never read of one <hi>Gama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liel</hi> in the <hi>Convocation</hi> of the Scribes and Phariſees? Or of one <hi>Cranmer</hi> in the <hi>Six Articles Councel</hi> of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth? Or of one <hi>Paphthnutius</hi> in the <hi>Councel of Nice?</hi> If not, give us leave to tell you, we hope you will not from <hi>Arhdeacon</hi> riſe to be <hi>Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop;</hi> which if you ſhould, we ſhould fear to be forced to pluck out our eyes, becauſe you ſay they are weaker then yours, now you are ſet above us. Let, Sir, <hi>Junior Sophs</hi> judge, whether you have not diſputed like the Maſter of much Reaſon. But, Sir, your <hi>Magiſterial Swada</hi> vaniſhed, you appear as a <hi>Reſpondent,</hi> and ſay you lay the Axe to the Root of the Tree; and I will give you your due; you do ſtrike at the Principle which is the Radix of Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Argumentation: But, Sir, you ſeem no skilfull Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter; you ſtrike a blow which can never reach the Root, or once ſhake the Tree.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> argues, <hi>Miniſterial modification of publick Worſhip by perſonal abilities, is the formal act of the Miniſterial Office;</hi> and he puts his Reſpondent to aſſign any other: You moſt profoundly anſwer by denial, and then aſſign <hi>Miniſtration to be the formal act of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 109.</note> 
               <hi>Miniſterial Office.</hi> Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> I know will admit your Notion in the <hi>Genus,</hi> an inferior Miniſter of State, or Servant in a Family, muſt miniſter, as well as a Miniſter of the Goſpel: but that ſpecifical act which ſhall difference the <hi>ſpecial Miniſtrations of theſe ſpecial Relations,</hi> and ſeveral capacities, was the thing enquired; and what is the <hi>formalis ratio</hi> of the Miniſterial Office, in <hi>the miniſtration of ſolemn publick Worſhip,</hi> is the Queſtion. To tell us, <hi>Miniſtration is the formal act of miniſtration,</hi> is good Scepticiſm; <hi>Doloſus verſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in generalibus;</hi> the <hi>formal act</hi> of the Miniſterial Office is to <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> but <hi>quomodo?</hi> is the queſtion. To hold your Lord Biſhops Stirrup, or the Candle to an Archdeacon, will not ſure <hi>fulfil the miniſtery</hi> of a Goſpel Miniſter; yet it is <hi>miniſtration.</hi> In your next tell us what is the formal act of the <hi>Goſpel Miniſterial Office,</hi> which will ſpecifically difference it from <hi>miniſtration in the general;</hi> and then you will ſee little cauſe to cry out to <hi>make modification of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35054:4"/>
act,</hi> the <hi>act it ſelf,</hi> is <hi>to make apparel the man;</hi> for <hi>modification of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration</hi> came not into the queſtion; but that <hi>modification of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Worſhip</hi> is the <hi>formal act of Miniſtration,</hi> was and is aſſerted: and, Sir, the cutting and making of Cloth in ſuch and ſuch a ſhape, is the formal miniſtration of a Tailor, who will eaſily ſee your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to be a man of Clouts. But you paſs to the Objection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Impoſition and preſcription in Prayer and Sacraments, is applicable unto Preaching.</hi> To this you give a four-fold Anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A Sermon is never the worſe for being well digeſted.</hi> True; if it be the Preachers own meditation, much the better.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>If it be ſeen and allowed by Authority, I know no harm in it.</hi> Nor I neither: but this is not neceſſary.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>This courſe (if not endleſs) would more ſecure peace and ſolid edification of the Church.</hi> I deny that, unleſs by the Popiſh guard, <hi>Ignorance is the Mother of Devotion.</hi> But, Sir,</p>
            <p>What are theſe to a Sermon not <hi>ſtudied,</hi> much leſs <hi>digeſted</hi> by the Preacher? not <hi>communicated to,</hi> but <hi>compoſed by</hi> pretenders to Authority? making Miniſters to have no work to do <hi>qua</hi> Miniſters, but to read what they have written, which is the nature and form of <hi>Homilies,</hi> and theſe excluſively impoſed, which may as well be admitted as the <hi>Liturgie</hi>!</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>When Presbyterians do preach other mens printed Sermons.</hi> Name any ſuch, who ſo do, let them bear their blame; I know no Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians who ſo do: But if you, Sir, pleaſe to enquire in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of <hi>Chriſts-Church,</hi> or <hi>Martins Ludgate, London,</hi> or <hi>Henly</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> you may hear of Sons of the Church who ſtuck not to preach Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> own printed Sermons: But theſe are prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for <hi>Homilie Miniſtrations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You think there is <hi>a vaſt difference between Praying and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> is there not alſo a difference between theſe and <hi>Sacraments?</hi> Prove that <hi>Chriſt taught that Prayer may be compriſed in a ſhort Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice:</hi> He ſuggeſted <hi>matter,</hi> did he determine the <hi>mode, terms, words, and expreſſions of Prayer?</hi> If not, what avails this plea? There are not more <hi>various Texts</hi> in the Bible, then <hi>wants</hi> in the Church, and both are the Scene for the variety of Gifts to exerciſe upon. But Sir, your next makes work for the <hi>Terraefilius. Mr.</hi> Croftons <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Pariſh Clerk and People, is not to our prejudice, or his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; for they are a general part of the holy prieſthood St.</hi> Peter <hi>ſpeaks of, and it is their duty to bear a part in Gods ſolemn worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well levell'd, Doctor; I hope we ſhall no more hear of <hi>Clergie</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:35054:5"/>
diſtinct from <hi>Laitie:</hi> The <hi>Pariſh Clerk and People are part of the holy Prieſthood;</hi> very true: <hi>they ought to bear a part in Gods ſolemn worſhip;</hi> undoubtedly true: but muſt that part be <hi>miniſtration,</hi> ſuch <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration</hi> as is the <hi>formal act of Goſpel miniſtry?</hi> either ſo, or you have ſaid nothing; and if ſo, farewel <hi>Holy Orders,</hi> yea, ſolemn Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Miniſtery; a man may make himſelf a Prieſt: Enter In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>depency, the Archdeacon hath opened the door: <hi>All the Lords people are holy,</hi> the <hi>holy prieſthood; Ergo,</hi> may miniſter in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Office.</p>
            <p>Your next, concerning <hi>School-boys,</hi> doth ſuggeſt ſome Boy read Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Poſition to you; for otherwiſe, you might have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, he doth diſtinguiſh the <hi>Miniſterial Office,</hi> and <hi>Miniſterial Act:</hi> and tells you, <hi>a boy may perform the Act,</hi> and queries, Muſt he therefore be <hi>admitted to the Office?</hi> He never allowed a <hi>Butcher</hi> a <hi>blow at an holy Oxe or Lamb,</hi> becauſe <hi>he can kill them;</hi> he never al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Qualification to conferr an Office.</p>
            <p>Sir, upon what you have ſaid, Mr. <hi>Crofton appears</hi> not ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, nor condemned by others; but if a Jury of Freſh-men condemn not your Logick, you ſhall have my Vote to be <hi>Senior Lecturer.</hi> Ending your diſpute, you paſs to your former <hi>Swada,</hi> and affirm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Crofton, <hi>and his party are bound to ſubmit to the uſe of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Liturgie.</hi> Negatur. You undertake to prove it thus.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>To do whatſoever is morally poſſible, for uniformity and peace ſake, is your duty: But to ſubmit to the uſe of a preſcribed Liturgie is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally poſſible;</hi> Ergo, <hi>to the ſubmit to the uſe of a preſcribed Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>is your duty.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Though I could, in love to peace, I will not quarrel at the terms of your <hi>Major Propoſition,</hi> and deny it: but I deny your <hi>Minor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</hi> (viz.) <hi>To ſubmit to the uſe of a preſcribed Liturgie, is not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally peſſible.</hi> You proceed to prove this.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is not ſinfull, and is within our natural power, is morally poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: But to ſubmit to a preſcribed Liturgie is not ſinful, and is within our natural power;</hi> Ergo, <hi>To ſubmit to the uſe of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcibed Liturgie is morally poſſible.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is allowed you; the <hi>Minor,</hi> as to the laſt Branch may be allowed you: but ſometimes our natural power may be under <hi>violent reſtraint,</hi> and then poſſibility may fail.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt branch, it is denied; and you proceed to prove it, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that to <hi>ſubmit to the uſe of a preſcribed Liturgie is not ſinfull;</hi> and you thus argue:</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:35054:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is forbidden by no Law, is not ſinfull: But to ſubmit to the uſe of a preſcribed Liturgie, is forbidden by no Law;</hi> Ergo, <hi>To ſubmit to the uſe of a preſcribed Liturgie, is not ſinfull.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is allowed you; the <hi>Minor</hi> I deny: <hi>For to ſubmit to the uſe of a preſcribed Liturgie</hi> is forbidden in the <hi>firſt Command,</hi> which doth require faithfulneſs in the Office committed to us by the Lord himſelf; <hi>Miniſters of God</hi> cannot without ſin become the <hi>Miniſters of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. In ſpecialty; the Law of the Miniſterial Office, in its ſpecial nature, (which muſt give Rules to the Miniſters acts <hi>qua</hi> Miniſterial acts) doth forbid ſuch ſubmiſſion, as <hi>inconſiſtent with, and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the formal act of the Miniſterial Office,</hi> (viz.) <hi>modifying wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip by perſonal abilities,</hi> notwithſtanding what our Opponent hath urged to the contrary,</p>
            <p>3. The edifying of the Church by variety of Miniſterial Gifts, is a Law which doth forbid ſuch ſubmiſſion, as deſtructive to that end.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle indeed bids us hold faſt the <hi>form of wholſome words,</hi> but not to hold to the <hi>ſame words;</hi> to ſpeak the ſame things, but not in the ſame ſyllables: for if ſo, the Liturgie muſt be <hi>catholick</hi> to all Chriſtians, in all places and ages of the World, and that in the <hi>Greek Language onely.</hi> Had this Doctor read Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument on this Queſtion againſt D. G. he ſure would not have thus diſputed, <hi>[Submiſſion to Superiors is a duty;</hi> but our <hi>judicium rationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le</hi> muſt judge their Mandate to be <hi>licitum &amp; honeſtum,</hi> which in this caſe we cannot do; and then our Dilemma is manifeſt, <hi>Shall we obey God or man?</hi> judge you.</p>
            <p>Now, Sir, your holding your Concluſion is not in my power to hinder; but if your Premiſſes be not puſh'd down, let all men of reaſon judge.</p>
            <p>You have, Sir, been at the pains to tranſcribe Mr. <hi>Crofton's Creed</hi> in point of <hi>Church Communion;</hi> praeterea nihil; you deny no one Article, nor diſpute not againſt them: Herein then we are agreed; onely, Sir, let me tell you, that <hi>freedome from corruptions and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders</hi> muſt be ſecured to the Church by <hi>the ways God hath directed,</hi> not by <hi>words which men have dictated,</hi> and by their unwarranted power determined.</p>
            <p>I having repelled the aſſaults, and diſſipated the Forces of the <note place="margin">Jerubbaal Rediviv.</note> 
               <hi>Right,</hi> muſt now encounter the Left Wing of this <hi>Armado:</hi> In ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to which, my courage is checked by obſerving the <hi>Anteſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanus</hi> and Captain that appeareth in the Front; not afraid of his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35054:6"/>
force, but aſhamed that any called a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> ſhould engage in ſuch a <hi>Church-ſubverting deſign,</hi> and that with ſuch weapons which the moſt rigid Separatiſts will be aſhamed to take up: but be he Son or Brother, the Relation may reſtrain what the weight of the Warfare doth neceſſitate: With him therefore I muſt take a turn; the rather, for that many have ſounded in my ears his proud alarm, <q>That Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> himſelf cannot now have any thing to ſay againſt him, his opinion and practice, unleſs he mind to have the laſt word, and reſolve he will not be convinced. </q>That this man may not abide wiſe in his own conceit, I muſt once more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the Rebuke given him, and adviſe him, [to reflect the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full affectation of a Title which can no way appertain to him, <hi>(viz.) Jerubbaal;</hi> whereas <hi>Baal</hi> is not the object of his Plea, nor is he the <hi>Gideon</hi> that threw down and pleaded againſt <hi>Baal.</hi> With what face doth this man conclude the <hi>Common-Prayer Book</hi> is <hi>Baal,</hi> and not once conſider or reſolve Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> expoſtulations hereupon? <q>My good friend, let it be ſeriouſly reſolved, is there no differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>between <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah? Rome,</hi> and a Reformed Church? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reformat.</hi> not <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</hi> p. 26, 36.</note> a calling on God, the onely true God, in the Name of Chriſt, though in a defective, rude, confuſed, and unfitting order, and praying unto Saints and dumb Idols? Though our order of Divine Service be a <hi>Roman</hi> dreg of ſome dangerous diſtaſtefull influence, yet it is not Popery: Shall we not bleſs God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in <hi>England,</hi> as brought out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> though ſome <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh</hi> Veſtures, Rites, and Orders, which ought to be abandoned, are retained, yea, returned into her? </q>When theſe things are well reſolved, will not this <hi>Baal</hi> appear a <hi>babe of his fancy,</hi> without any real exiſtence? Knoweth not this <hi>Pleader,</hi> that the miſtake of the object doth miſ-guide the act, and make reproof a groundleſs calumny?</p>
            <p>But if the Liturgie muſt be accounted <hi>Baal,</hi> is this man the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubbaal?</hi> When? by what Plea? in whoſe judgment, except his own? Let me ſay over again what I ſaid in my laſt; hath not <hi>Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>written and preached againſt it? Hath not Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for his oppoſition to it? Doth not Mr.</hi> Croftons <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jerub. ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified,</hi> p. 2.</note> 
               <hi>againſt which this man appeareth, plead convincingly againſt it?</hi> The enemy being Judge, is there any more open <hi>Jerubbaal</hi> in our Age then Mr. <hi>Crofton?</hi> This man appeareth againſt Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and due bounds ſet unto mens affection; inferring what the premiſſes will not allow, and proudly affects to be called <hi>Jerubbaal:</hi> Oh vanity! oh folly! But</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:35054:6"/>
Secondly, I would adviſe this Combatant to review what he hath written; for verily I cannot without grief and ſhame, obſerve the <hi>Non-ſence, ignorance,</hi> and <hi>errour,</hi> with which this unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable Peice aboundeth: I ſhall, for his humiliation, note it in each Paragraph of his Book; and the rather, becauſe his wild and confuſed method admits no regular Ratiocination. Note there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
            <p>His Preface enters with an out-cry, That <hi>the Rebuke</hi> I laſt gave him <hi>(being big-bellied with Satyrical invectives, ſlanders, and revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings)</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jerubb. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviv.</hi> p. 1.</note> 
               <hi>would better become a</hi> Shimei, <hi>then a</hi> Levite: But he ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not one <hi>revilingterm;</hi> how big-bellied ſoever the Rebuke <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared,</hi> it is manifeſt no one was brought forth: I muſt therefore tell mine Antagoniſt, ſtubborn and ſcornfull Sons do conclude the Fathers juſt Rebukes are <hi>railing;</hi> let ſober men judge the ſobriety of ſo juſt Rebukes, as his <hi>Jerubbaal</hi> provoked.</p>
            <p>His next Paragraph complaineth, that he was charged with a <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take,</hi> a <hi>total miſtake,</hi> a <hi>groſs miſtake,</hi> which he ſaith, is to him <hi>matter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 2.</note> 
               <hi>of wonder;</hi> and <hi>to whom can it be other, who is but in the leaſt acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the occaſion, end and ſcope of his writings.</hi> I cannot but note the clearneſs of his Reaſon, or rather <hi>non-ſence</hi> of his Argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> blamed (he ſaith <hi>cenſured)</hi> his <hi>non-communion</hi> at <hi>Lawrence Jewry Church-door,</hi> and demanded (he ſaith <hi>challenged)</hi> an anſwer to his <hi>Reformation not Separation:</hi> this gave occaſion to his writing; he aimed at truth and duty, that was the ſcope and end of his writing. All this admitted, what followeth? That it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible he ſhould <hi>miſtake, totally miſtake, groſly miſtake?</hi> So that he muſt hence wonder to be charged therewith; and all the world knowing this occaſion, and end, cannot but wonder with him. An exact <hi>Marks-man,</hi> that provoked to ſhoot, and intending well, is thereby put under an impoſſibility of miſſing the Mark! But could he think, all men will judge the <hi>occaſion and end</hi> of his undertaking would ſo clear his underſtanding, as to keep him from miſtake? If good intentions could deſtroy an erroneous judgment, there would not be ſo many <hi>miſtakes</hi> in the world as there is: Be the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion and end of this mans undertaking what it will, was he not miſtaken in Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> when he called him, printed him the <hi>Mae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenas and Advocate for the Engliſh Liturgie?</hi> Is it not out of <hi>miſtake,</hi> that in this ſecond piece he ſaith, <hi>The Altar of Baal, by him thrown down, is by me repaired, and my deſign is its reſurrection?</hi> Reſult not theſe terms of propriety; <hi>Your</hi> novum organum, <hi>your man-deviſed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35054:7"/>
Liturgie, your Divine Service, your blaſted Liturgie,</hi> out the total and groſs miſtake of Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> and his Plea; Will this man have <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jerubb. Rediviv.</hi> p. 11, 13, 14, 17.</note> the impudence to juſtifie the Calumny of the wicked, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>is an Apoſtate, revolted from what he witneſſed?</hi> Let him draw it into an Indictment; Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſhall abide the trial, though his Jury be a pack of his worſt enemies, of <hi>ſuperſtitious Sons of the Church, and ſeparating Sects.</hi> I could, for the honour of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wiſh, that men had not more cauſe to wonder that this man can do nothing but miſtake, and perſiſt with folly in a miſtake, as it is too manifeſt in this his ſecond Tract; then to wonder, that notwithſtanding his good occaſion and end, he was <hi>miſtaken, totally miſtaken, groſly miſtaken;</hi> for the laſt is incident to the beſt of men.</p>
            <p>His third Paragraph tells us of <hi>five Quaeries, on Reſolution of which dependeth the deciſion of this controverſie.</hi> But, Sir, my laſt drew the <note place="margin">Pag. 3.</note> Controverſie to a much narrower Criſis; one ſingle Queſtion, which well reſolved, would end this ſtrife, <hi>(viz.) Whether the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie, being an unlawfully conſtituted mode of ſolemn publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, be ſo far unlawfull, or unlawfull in that kind or quality of unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, which will conſtitute a warrantable ground or reaſon for non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communion in the worſhip of God miniſtred by the ſame?</hi> Jerubbaal ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtif. <hi>p.</hi> 25. Near this queſtion you do not, you dare not come; your War would be too ſoon ended, and your wordy Army too ſoon disbanded, if you ſhould fight ſo cloſe. Sir, have you ſtudied no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Sceptiſciſm, to avoid the Queſtion by multiplying Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of your own framing? Are you a <hi>Sopbomore,</hi> ſo ſubtil to ſhun the Queſtion ſtated, and diſpute the Quaeries of your own brain? You may, Sir, be your own Antagoniſt all your days, with much eaſe and pleaſure to your fancy, but with little profit to others. Yet before you buckle to your work, you ſay you will <hi>enfeeble my Plea,</hi> which you can more ſtoutly call <hi>cavils and excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> then convincingly gain-ſay or contradict.</p>
            <p>The fourth Paragraph doth therefore obſerve the <hi>Criſis</hi> of Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Plea to be <hi>communion in Gods worſhip miniſtred by the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie,</hi> not <hi>communion in the Miniſterial mode:</hi> but this obſerved, is paſſed with a ſcornfull note of <hi>Crambe recocta, occurring 20. times;</hi> not once conſidering it was ſo frequently inculcated on deſign to clear his dull capacity, who could, or would not obſerve it in Mr. <hi>Crofton's Reform. not Separat.</hi> And, Sir, I yet ſee not but this <hi>Crambe recocta</hi> may be diſht up to you 200. <hi>times,</hi> before you will digeſt the ſame: <hi>Solomon</hi> hath indeed told us, though we <hi>bray a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35054:7"/>
fool in a mortar, he will not underſtand.</hi> I wiſh you had turned on the hinge of the controverſie; I ſhould deny learned ſelf to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any ſtrenuous argumentation, which would demonſtrate this forcible Plea to be what you pleaſe to call it. a <hi>plauſible evaſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fifth Paragraph fills time and paper to tell men, what he <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> that runneth may read, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Mr. Croftons <hi>diſpute is about popular, not Miniſterial communion.</hi> Yet here I cannot but obſerve his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the Queſtion; which he ſaith is, <hi>Whether this communion be Duty?</hi> He ſhould obſerve, it is the <hi>Licet,</hi> not the <hi>Debet,</hi> of this <hi>communion,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> doth affirm; he never diſputed this Communion to be a <hi>duty</hi> binding <hi>ſemper,</hi> but <hi>lawfull,</hi> and <hi>made duty</hi> by <hi>inevitable neceſſity</hi> onely: He always affirms Communion with a <hi>non obſtante,</hi> notwithſtanding the <hi>Liturgie;</hi> and onely, when we <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have ſolemn publick worſhip without the ſame:</hi> the utmoſt of Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> affirmation is, <hi>The Liturgie maketh not a warrantable ground for ſeceſſion from Gods Church and worſhip.</hi> But this mans good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt make all men wonder he ſhould be charged <hi>to miſtake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet, Sir, you are well skill'd in a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, when you tell us, <note place="margin">Pag. 4.</note> 
               <hi>You had reaſon confidently to affirm, Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>ſaid, the Liturgie or Common-Prayer is an act of ſolemn publick worſhip.</hi> This denied, you plead a paſſage which onely ſeems to ſuggeſt it; and in which it is not ſaid: Is, Sir, this the ſtrife about words condemned by the Apoſtle, for a man to deny he ſpake what he is unjuſtly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to have ſpoken? But of this enough, it being perſonal. But, Sir, I cannot a little wonder at your ſtrange confidence, in again fathering the fancie of your own brain on Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> in what you call his <hi>Dumb Argument,</hi> when you know it hath in his name been diſowned; and the abominable ſequel thereof, together with its inconſiſtency with his Queſtion, and the ſcope of his Plea been ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrated in my <hi>Jerub. juſtif.</hi> p. 5. 6. Can you out-face me, and Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> too, that he <hi>will not after recollection ſay, that is a monſtrous Argument,</hi> which maketh the Liturgie <hi>eſſential to the ſanctification of the Lords day,</hi> ſo as that the <hi>Lords day</hi> cannot be ſanctified where the Service book is not attended, aſſented to, and acted in? and doth not this naturally flow from your fancied con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion? Were you not rebuked for this in my laſt? and was not Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Argument put into form, that you might ſee its force; Man, be not obſtinate.</p>
            <p>The ſixth Paragraph doth aſſert a Notion, which admitted, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſet forms of Prayer <hi>eſſential</hi> to Communion in all ſolemn pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35054:8"/>
Prayer, <hi>(viz.) The Adhibition of his</hi> Amen <hi>is as real communion in the Miniſterial mode of worſhip, as the perſonal acting by conclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, popular reſponds, and groundleſs variation of geſture, and the like.</hi> Sir, I agree with you, <hi>magis &amp; minus non variant ſpeciem:</hi> Prove Mr. <hi>Crofton's Amen</hi> to be as <hi>real,</hi> though not ſo <hi>extenſive communion</hi> as the fore-mentioned perſonal acts, and I will undertake he ſhall retract his principle and practice too. But, Sir, you are the firſt that ever made the <hi>external miniſterial mode</hi> the adaequate object of the peoples <hi>Amen;</hi> all others referr it to the <hi>matter,</hi> and the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter onely:</hi> and truly, Sir, if it be true, I muſt be excuſed, if I refuſe to joyn with a <hi>Scotch-man</hi> in Prayer; for they are, of all men, no little incident to diſorder, in their conceived, ſelf-framed Prayers. Nor do I ſee how I can be ſecured againſt the guilt of that confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and diſorder of expreſſion to which all men are ſubject, ſave onely by <hi>ſeeing</hi> the Form of Prayer to which I muſt give mine <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and being well aſſured from it the Miniſter ſhall not vary: This, Sir, neceſſitateth a <hi>Liturgie,</hi> and was ſuggeſted to you in my laſt, had you pleaſed to obſerve it. Sir, I judged <hi>Amen</hi> to be the act of my <hi>judicium diſcretionis,</hi> to be adhibited as mine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding apprehended the matter prayed for: I have heard ſome Petitions put up to God, which I durſt not enforce with my <hi>Amen.</hi> I preſume you will not deny to pray with me; and yet (as you and I ſtand informed) you could not adhibit your <hi>Amen</hi> to all that I muſt ask of God. I conceive, if my <hi>Amen</hi> be at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of mine Underſtanding, in reference to any <hi>matter,</hi> it is much more ſuch in reference to <hi>every external Form,</hi> and <hi>Miniſterial mode</hi> of Prayer. And now, Sir, Mr. <hi>Crofton's Nuntio</hi> will tell you, that admitting the <hi>Smectymnuan obſervation of the Letany</hi> (which holds not in any part, ſave the Deprecations, and that alſo is diſputable) to be true: Mr. <hi>Crofton's judicium diſeretionis</hi> commanding his <hi>Amen,</hi> can direct and diſpoſe a <hi>ſilent obſervation</hi> of ſuch a <hi>popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar interruptions</hi> to ſolemn publick Worſhip. Sir, if you will make <hi>Amen</hi> contract the Guilt of the mode of Prayer, you muſt go to work again; for I will confidently affirm, in this opinion you ſtand alone, and will ſtand alone.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh Paragraph is the wild frolick of a fooliſh fancy; as if my noting the <hi>Liturgie</hi> to be a <hi>political order and direction,</hi> did <note place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> confound it with the <hi>Directory;</hi> this is a vanity ſo viſible, that I will ſay no more to it, ſave this, If you have no more wit then to play with your ſhadow, enjoy your ſport; what is this to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion in diſpute?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:35054:8"/>
The eighth Paragraph is like the ſeventh: In it you note, with <note place="margin">Pag. 7.</note> ſeeming pity, Mr. <hi>Crofton's neceſſity of practice in priſon;</hi> but, good Sir, what <hi>neceſſity</hi> (more then that of conſcience and duty) conſtrained Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> to ſtate the <hi>Principle</hi> he now aſſerts, when he was at liberty, worſhipping God in purity and power, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting the late Biſhop of <hi>Worceſters</hi> advancing the <hi>Liturgie?</hi> Deal you faithfully with God, his Cauſe, and People, when you ſuggeſt Mr. <hi>Crofton's now principle and practice was extorted by a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent neceſſity?</hi> The Lord judge theſe Cenſures. (2.) Your Notion of <hi>Civil preſence</hi> comes again to be obſerved. (3.) It is well the Plea of neceſſity groweth <hi>frivolous to you;</hi> it is not ſo to others; they miſs ſome <hi>integrals of Worſhip.</hi> (4.) I ſhould be loth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, <hi>ſet Forms of Preaching and Prayer</hi> (with ſoundneſs of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in both) were <hi>England's Ichabod;</hi> theſe were impoſed, and all Preaching ſilenced, for ſome time, by the Proclamation of King <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. and Gods Ark and Glory was then returning: I wiſh not to ſee ſo dark a cloud in Gods Sanctuary; yet fear to conclude (if a lawfull Miniſtry and ſubſtantial Ordinances abide) that Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is removed. I yet fear to <hi>eat your bread of ſecreſie,</hi> and to drink <hi>your ſtollen waters, though ſweet,</hi> leſt the <hi>dead be there,</hi> and ſuch <hi>gueſts be in the depths of Hell.</hi> The houſe of an <hi>Obed-edom</hi> may entertain an <hi>exiled Ark;</hi> but not have comfort, or give any guard to <hi>Corah's company.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ninth Paragraph is, in my judgment, an eminent piece of <note place="margin">P. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> Non-ſence: To my Objection, <hi>The perſonal guilt of</hi> Hophni <hi>and</hi> Phineas <hi>could not defile the Church;</hi> you anſwer, <hi>Perſonal corruptions are there contra-diſtinct to real, not to publick, as it ſeems you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand me.</hi> Good Sir, what underſtand you by <hi>real corruptions?</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions indeed? Is not all <hi>perſonal</hi> corruptions <hi>real</hi> corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Are perſonal faults onely imaginary guilt? It is then good ſinning alone. Sir, I never underſtood <hi>real</hi> oppoſed to <hi>perſonal,</hi> but it ſignified <hi>publick.</hi> Conſider well how Civilians and Caſuiſts diſtinguiſh an Oath into <hi>reale</hi> &amp; <hi>perſonale;</hi> and tell me what you underſtand by <hi>real,</hi> diſtinct from publick, and oppoſed to perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, that I may underſtand you.</p>
            <p>The tenth Paragraph doth enforce the neceſſity of a groundleſs diſtinction of <hi>participation by profeſſion,</hi> and <hi>joynt communion;</hi> but addeth no new matter, onely referreth to <hi>Jerubbaal:</hi> This then I turn back to <hi>Jerubbaal juſtified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The eleventh Paragraph noteth, that <hi>Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>will deny that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 8.</note>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:35054:9"/>
               <hi>there are many, or indeed any members of the Church catholick, who never had opportunity of aſſociating themſelves with, or of joynt commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the ſolemn worſhip of God, in a particular Church:</hi> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth the ſame with needleſs diſtinctions, and manifeſt non-ſence. As (1.) by <hi>univerſal is meant the catholick militant Church, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending viſible and inviſible;</hi> yet note, his <hi>Jerubbaal</hi> did deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it to be <hi>viſible onely,</hi> pa. 19. and the catholick Church muſt be the <hi>ſubject</hi> of ſolemn publick Worſhip, and Gods Ordinances, capable of <hi>aſſociation and joynt communion in them;</hi> of theſe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible part of the Church are not capable. (2.) That a man may be a <hi>member of the inviſible, without opportunity of joynt communion in outward Ordinances.</hi> I do not onely imply, but I ſpeak out; but what is this to our purpoſe? Nor will I deny, a <hi>profeſſor</hi> may be a <hi>believer;</hi> but that maketh him not a <hi>member of the Church viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:</hi> Profeſſion is the <hi>ground</hi> of viſible Church-memberſhip, but it is not the <hi>formalis ratio</hi> thereof; no; that is <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> an act of <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal aſſociation, and joynt communion;</hi> which muſt needs have its opportunity in all that enjoy it. I ſay as his greater Sophies, (ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly quoted) <hi>A profeſſor is viſible, a believer inviſible;</hi> the <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever</hi> may be a <hi>profeſſor of the ſame faith,</hi> and <hi>not partake in the ſame ordinances:</hi> Yet it will not hence follow, there are <hi>any or many members of the Church viſible, who never had an opportunity of joynt communion in ſolemn publick worſhip;</hi> for all ſuch muſt be incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> without which, the beſt profeſſors and true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers muſt be <hi>foro Eccleſiae</hi> judged <hi>without the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twelfth Paragraph, concerning Conventicles, tells us, <hi>A ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of perſons, ten, twenty, thirty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or forty, amongſt whom is a Miniſter ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrating true Divine Worſhip, according to the will of Chriſt, by the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his Spirit, and in his Name; not cauſeleſly and unjuſtly ſeparating from a true Church, is no Conventicle, or Schiſmatical Aſſembly.</hi> Who ever ſaid ſuch an Aſſembly was a <hi>Conventicle? Jerubbaal ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified</hi> told you of twenty, thirty, or forty <hi>private members,</hi> aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled <note place="margin">Pag. 22.</note> 
               <hi>diſtinct from,</hi> and <hi>oppoſite to a Church,</hi> an holy Convocation: And I ſay again, if the Congregations in <hi>England</hi> be <hi>true Churches,</hi> and ſeceſſion from them (as it yet ſeemeth to be) <hi>unwarrantable and groundleſs;</hi> though twenty, thirty, or forty, with a Miniſter, conſtitute themſelves a <hi>counter-Church, oppoſite to theſe Aſſemblies,</hi> and therein adminiſter <hi>Church-ordinances;</hi> I ſee not how to acquit them from the repute and reality of a <hi>Conventicle,</hi> and <hi>Schiſmatical Aſſembly:</hi> Nor will Chriſt's promiſe of his preſence be any prop
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35054:9"/>
to their Fabrick, who are not met in his Name; for <hi>God is a God of Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are at length arrived to his five Quaeries before mentioned; <note place="margin">Pag. 9.</note> by himſelf ſtated, and ſo beſt reſolved.</p>
            <p>The firſt is this; <hi>What is that which may warrant and acquit from</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Quaer. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Schiſm, a perſons non-communion with the Church of</hi> England <hi>in the worſhip alledged to be miniſtred by her Liturgie, or Common-Prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt here note, that though he come not cloſe to the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in diſpute, yet he cometh ſomewhat nearer; and can now men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the <hi>ſubject, Worſhip,</hi> diſtinct from his <hi>adjunct,</hi> the <hi>Liturgie</hi> by which it is miniſtred: ſo that he hath learned to ſpeak in an entire Propoſition, <hi>worſhip miniſtred by the Liturgie;</hi> I hope he hath ſo clear reaſon as to diſcern the <hi>ſubject, Worſhip:</hi> the <hi>Predicate mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by the Liturgie,</hi> are the parts of this Propoſition; and the <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip miniſtred,</hi> not the <hi>Liturgical miniſtration,</hi> is the object of his Communion, or non-Communion, controverted under this Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; which he reſolveth in certain Propoſitions, whereof the firſt is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Communion with this part of the Church is a Duty,</hi> &amp;c. This is ſquare to Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> aſſertion; onely I would adviſe him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe <note place="margin">1 Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit.</note> the wording of it, for it ſoundeth non-ſence in mine ears.</p>
            <p>He noteth an Objection, <hi>Reading the Word is a publick Ordinance</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 10.</note> 
               <hi>of God, and part of publick Worſhip:</hi> He anſwereth, <hi>True; who ever denied the thing is appointed?</hi> but not <hi>the meaſure,</hi> or <hi>quantum; be enjoyeth it in Textual occaſional Reading in the Sermon preached.</hi> But, good Sir, is not <hi>ſolemn Reading,</hi> diſtinct from, and oppoſite to <hi>textual and occaſional Reading,</hi> a part of ſolemn Worſhip? Caſt your eye on <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8. 3. <hi>Luke</hi> 4. 16. <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 15, 27. 15. 21. Conſult the practiſe of the Jews, and primitive Chriſtians, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations of Fathers, ancient and modern Divines Systems, and Common-places in Divinity, eſpecially Expoſitions on the fourth Commandment, tell me which of them aſſert not <hi>ſolemn Reading, diſtinct from Preaching and its accidents,</hi> to be a diſtinct part of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn publick worſhip? and which of them will conclude <hi>textual and occaſional Reading</hi> to be the performance of it? Is not your fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in this manifeſtly ridiculous?</p>
            <p>The ſecond Propoſition reſolving this Quaerie, is a moſt ſtrange, <note place="margin">2 Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit.</note> ranting, uncharitable (if I may not ſay impious) Notion, <hi>(viz.) The worſhip adminiſtred, or adminiſtrable by the Engliſh Liturgie, or publick ſet-Form, conſidered as ſuch, and in a complex ſtate, appeareth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35054:10"/>
(as yet) to be none of that Worſhip of which God is the Author, the Goſpel the Rule, the practice Apoſtolick the pattern; but</hi> Cultus adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terinus, <hi>meer adulterate worſhip, a piece of Superſtition, arbitrary Devotion, Scripture-bitten will-worſhip, ſupererogatory ſervice, Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruck Tradition and Ordinance of Man.</hi> Whither will the man run? This proved, is enough to warrant, yea, to neceſſitate ſeceſſion from the Engliſh Church: but we muſt believe it on the Magiſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al confident <hi>ſay-ſo</hi> of this Grave Dictator; for no proof is ſo much as offered. But doth the man know what he ſaith? or whereof he doth affirm? that he thus ranteth, not againſt the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> (that may be born) but againſt the <hi>worſhip in abſtracto,</hi> diſtinct from the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie,</hi> is to me very ſtrange. The Worſhip <hi>adminiſtred, or admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrable</hi> by the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> is <hi>cultus adulterinus,</hi> no <hi>worſhip of God,</hi> is his Poſition; the moſt rigid Separatiſts will not ſay it. If this be ſo, well might Doctor <hi>Owen</hi> acquit Independency from Schiſm, by pleading the <hi>Church loſt its being under Popery;</hi> gathering of Churches muſt needs be a duty; yet no gathered Church hath <hi>any worſhip of God,</hi> or any other the <hi>cultus adulterinus,</hi> &amp;c. for they have no other worſhip then what is <hi>adminiſtrable by the Engliſh Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie.</hi> Good Sir, what is the <hi>worſhip adminiſtred or adminiſtrable by the Engliſh Liturgie?</hi> Is it not <hi>ſolemn reading the Scriptures, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of God, Baptiſm and the Lords Supper?</hi> Pray you, Sir, is not <hi>God the Author, Goſpel the Rule, and practice Apoſtolick the Pattern of theſe?</hi> If theſe be not the <hi>worſhip adminiſtred, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrable by the Liturgie,</hi> give us the name of it, that we may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire its nature: Proteſtants have had no other worſhip ſince King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth his dayes; true Chriſtians have had no other ſince <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> his dayes: have the one and other been left in approach to God <hi>without his worſhip?</hi> yea, with <hi>adulterate wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> &amp;c. How much will this fall ſhort of Blaſphemy, not onely againſt Proteſtants, but Chriſtians, and the God of both? I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, I tremble that I hold you ſo cloſe to the <hi>Criſis of our Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie,</hi> that you ſhould break out with ſuch a <hi>ranting notion,</hi> which doth raze the <hi>foundation of the Church.</hi> Your <hi>ſenſu compoſito in individuo, connexio &amp; qua talis,</hi> will not relieve you; for mean you what you will by theſe, the <hi>worſhip in abſtracto</hi> is the <hi>ſubject</hi> of theſe, and of your Propoſition, predicated <hi>cultus adulterinus,</hi> &amp;c. And, Sir, leſt we ſhould miſtake you, you have not onely explained it by the actual adminiſtration; <hi>worſhip adminiſtred</hi> would not ſerve your turn, but you add the very <hi>poſſe</hi> thereof, and determine
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35054:10"/>
againſt the <hi>worſhip adminiſtrable by the Engliſh Liturgie.</hi> You may, Sir, by this notion help the ſimple to blaſphemous words; but can never make a ſober underſtanding Proſelyte, or obtain any ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſecond, that knoweth how to underſtand a Propoſition: Yet this fancy I find to be the Line which hath led you into the Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth in which you are intangled. Be ſerious, and ſee whether it be not the ſnare of the Devil; out of which the Lord redeem you.</p>
            <p>On this Notion you proceed to reſolve Objections: of which you note,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is in the Common-Prayer the ſubſtance of Divine worſhip,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Object.</note> 
               <hi>though diſorderly adminiſtred; the eſſential form of Prayer, a calling upon God in the Name of Chriſt for things agreeable to his will,</hi> &amp;c. To this you anſwer, conceding the <hi>matter of the Petitions, as that you will not diſpute;</hi> and I ſuppoſe you will not queſtion the matter of the Sacraments. The <hi>Form you deny not;</hi> onely follow your fancy, <hi>the Name of Chriſt;</hi> which, you ſay, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> hath <hi>with diſdain diſowned.</hi> That I, in Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> name, <hi>diſowned</hi> it, is true; the <hi>diſdain</hi> is your own fancy: What one word of diſdain is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed? I will tranſcribe my ſentence, that you and others may obſerve why and how I do diſown this ſence of the Name of Chriſt. <q>Sir, I will aſſure you, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> did not underſtand by the Name of Chriſt, the Will of Chriſt; and yet I muſt tell him, it <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jerub. juſt.</hi> p. 27.</note> is but one Doctors opinion, that this is not a right deſcription of Prayer: He might have been pleaſed to obſerve, in the ſame page, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> determined the matter muſt be according to the Will of God; and Will of Chriſt doth require ſome adjunct qualities which come not into the definition; but in <hi>the Name of Chriſt;</hi> that is, for his ſake, merits, and mediation, cannot be left out.</q> Note, Sir, <hi>The Name of Chriſt doth not exclude the Will of Chriſt;</hi> both have their places, and due reſpect: <hi>the will of Chriſt,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the <hi>matter,</hi> is eſſential; the <hi>name of Chriſt,</hi> in reference to the <hi>form,</hi> is made eſſential; the <hi>will of Chriſt,</hi> in reference to the <hi>mode,</hi> in adjunct qualities, <hi>gravity of expreſſion, fervency of affection,</hi> and <hi>reverence in demeanour,</hi> is made neceſſary, but not eſſential: And from what Divine doth Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> differ in this diſtribution of the parts of Prayer? For herein (to uſe your own terms) <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> in genere, <hi>is worſhip; and</hi> in ſpecie, <hi>ſuch inſtituted worſhip.</hi> But you proceed, and ſay;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I mutter;</hi> Sir, I ſpeak it out, <hi>The will of Chriſt requires gravity</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 11.</note> 
               <hi>in expeſſion, reverence in demeanour,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>which come not into the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35054:11"/>
of Prayer, as eſſential to its form.</hi> Nor, Sir, can you gain-ſay this: and, Sir, it would ſeem, yea, it really is ſo, that if the <hi>eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial form of Prayer</hi> depend upon, or conſiſt in a <hi>conformity to the will of Chriſt,</hi> that no Prayer is ſuch, but what hath thoſe qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations: for, Sir, if ſo, a vain thought, and word, or rude demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, doth deſtroy the Prayer. But you ſay;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Two Commandments are confounded.</hi> But, Sir, by whom? is it not by your ſelf in your very preſent diſtinction? For you ſay, <hi>the</hi> modus, <hi>outward manner of worſhip doth belong to the ſecond Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pa. 12, 13, 14, 15.</note> cujus contrarium verum eſt.</p>
            <p>You enter a diſcourſe of your Orthodoxie; in which if you be not Heterodox, I have no skill in Divinity. I will not ſtrictly ſcan each word, yout diſcourſe is wild; but theſe Notions are obvious.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That calling on God in the Name of Chriſt is required in the third</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pa. 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>Command.</hi> And yet, Sir, this is the <hi>forma informans</hi> of Prayer as inſtituted Worſhip; for Nature will teach men to call on God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The external mode of Prayer doth belong to the ſecond Command.</hi> And yet it is not eſſential to Prayer, as inſtituted Worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Prayer which is not agreeable for neceſſary modes and qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as gravity of expreſſion, reverence in demeanour,</hi> &amp;c. to the third Commandment, may be juſtly denied <hi>to have the compleat eſſential form of inſtituted worſhip.</hi> If this be true, Prayer it ſelf is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſinfull men, and glorified Saints need it not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The miniſterial mode in Prayer is</hi> medium cultus; Which you were told is but <hi>cultus vehiculum:</hi> the <hi>medium</hi> is <hi>invocation,</hi> the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial mode is onely the <hi>vocal inſtrument</hi> between God and the people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Praying by the Liturgie is as praying before an Image:</hi> And yet in the one the <hi>Image,</hi> in the other, <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>God onely,</hi> is the proximate immediate object of the Prayer: Men praying by the Liturgie, paſs to God himſelf, <hi>nullo medio interveniente;</hi> but praying to an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, ſets God at a diſtance, and ſalutes his Gentleman Uſher.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe and the like Notions you inferr your principle, and juſtifie what I thought you would have retracted with grief and ſhame, <hi>That God is not worſhipped by the Liturgie.</hi> Hereupon, you frivolouſly, and to no purpoſe, mention many Authors: I pray you ſtudy in what they have written on the third Command, with this note; <q>Many things are noted as ſinfull, to be avoided and abandoned, which yet exiſting do not vitiate the ſubject, nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35054:11"/>
Gods Worſhip about which they do converſe, and will not therefore warrant ſeceſſion or ſepration.</q>
            </p>
            <p>You highly inſult in my conceſſion the <hi>Liturgie is evil, a poſitive evil.</hi> I grant it you again: but, Sir, is there no <hi>evil, poſitive evil,</hi> but againſt the ſecond Commandment? Is all <hi>evil, poſitive evil,</hi> in other mens act, a warrant for my ſeparation? And now let us come again to the Queſtion; Is the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> though <hi>evil,</hi> a <hi>poſitive evil,</hi> ſuch an <hi>evil,</hi> an evil of that <hi>kind and quality, as to warrant ſeparation?</hi> If not, what do you gain by what I grant? I tell you, the Liturgie is not <hi>medium cultus</hi> within the ſecond Command; but <hi>modus miniſterialis</hi> within the third Command. Be it ſuperſtitions, your ſelf confeſs it is not Idolatry.</p>
            <p>To your Quaery concerning the <hi>Corinthian prayers in an unknown tongue;</hi> I ſay, <hi>God</hi> was not the <hi>object;</hi> things according to his will <note place="margin">Pag. 15.</note> was not the <hi>matter,</hi> nor was the <hi>Name of Chriſt</hi> the <hi>form</hi> thereof; for there was no invocation, there being <hi>vox &amp; praeterea nihil;</hi> men heard a voice, but for what, to whom, or through whom it was uttered, they underſtood not: Now, Sir, is this the Caſe of the Liturgie?</p>
            <p>Sir, not to inſiſt on your confuſed diſcourſes of ſuperſtition; that there is <hi>evil, poſitive evil,</hi> in the Liturgie, I deny not; that I, or Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> are <hi>Advocates for it,</hi> or the <hi>evils of it,</hi> I do deny: but being convinced all <hi>evil</hi> will not warrant <hi>ſeparation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> here I ſtick, and here I hold you; Is the Liturgie <hi>ſuch an evil,</hi> of <hi>ſuch kind and quality,</hi> as to conſtitute a warrantable ground of ſeceſſion or ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration? I yet ſtand negative: Come to the Queſtion, and prove that; for <hi>affirmanti incidit probatio.</hi> Your wild diſcourſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Commandments and Superſtition being paſt, you proceed to anſwer another Objection by me made.</p>
            <p>God (ſay you) is not worſhipped by the Liturgie; the <hi>manner</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 17.</note> 
               <hi>and form is humane.</hi> To which I objected, So is the <hi>form and mode of a ſtudied Sermon, and conceived Prayer; is not God worſhipped by them?</hi> To this you firſt anſwer by manifeſt miſtake: the <hi>worſhip is called hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, of which man is not onely agent, but author.</hi> But my Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not of the <hi>Worſhip adminiſtred, or adminiſtrable;</hi> but of the <hi>Liturgie, manner and dreſs adminiſtring:</hi> and hereof I affirm, God hath appointed men to be not onely <hi>Agents,</hi> but <hi>Authors,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their wiſdome and faithfulneſs, as Miniſters; though that be appointed, yet this is arbitrarily eligible by men apted and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed thereto. Your ſecond Anſwer, telling us, you call it <hi>humane</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:35054:12"/>
becauſe it proceeds from man originally, is inſignificant; for as an external and miniſterial mode, it is not <hi>within the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> nor <hi>contrary to Chriſts Crown Prerogative,</hi> but conſonant thereto; for Chriſt, as King of his Church, hath committed his mind to his Embaſſadors, and charged them by their own wiſdome and faithfulneſs to put his Worwip into a due mode, ſuitable to his Majeſty, and his peoples weakneſs; and this you muſt know is bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomed on the nature of the Miniſterial Office, that Scripture Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept; and is juſtified by the preſident of the Apoſtles practice, who were the Authors of that mode and dreſs by which they miniſtred: If then you fancy mans <hi>wiſdome of compoſition of Prayer and Sermon in general,</hi> and <hi>mans will in impoſition of his own compoſed mode,</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the <hi>will and wiſdome of God,</hi> your ſelf, and all Miniſters in Gods Church are hereof Guilty; yet they neither may, nor muſt avoid it. Your third Anſwer is, That the <hi>eſſential form of worſhip adminiſtred by the Common-Prayer is juſtly denied and diſproved.</hi> That, Sir, it is <hi>boldly</hi> denied, is very true; but not <hi>juſtly;</hi> nor yet diſproved, I confidently affirm: Yet, Sir, I muſt pull in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, if <hi>the worſhip adminiſtred and adminiſtrable by the Liturgie be not Gods worſhip:</hi> When this is proved, I ſhall know in what ſence <hi>God is not worſhipped by the Liturgie:</hi> but I hope you will find out other worſhip of God not adminiſtrable by the Liturgie; for Word, Prayer, and Sacraments, you affirm, are <hi>cultus adulterinus.</hi> Your fourth Anſwer cannot but make Liturgical men to laugh: <hi>Studied Sermon, and conceived Prayer,</hi> you ſay, cannot be ſaid to be <hi>humane;</hi> (you muſt mean, in the Miniſterial mode and dreſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by mans judgment;) for <hi>though Man is the Agent, he is Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of neither;</hi> yet the one and the other is the act of his invention and judgment: <hi>Chriſt hath directed Preaching and Praying in an edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying manner and method, and therefore the Miniſterial mode is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in the Word:</hi> Oh rare Logick! The Lord Major requires his meat be carved in an handſom and honorable manner; therefore he determines the ſpecial carving mode. Your next conceſſion, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>exegetical,</hi> or <hi>analytical,</hi> or <hi>paraphraſtical Preaching,</hi> &amp; the <hi>word<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Prayer,</hi> is contradictory to this inference; and yet, in the heighth of non-ſence, you proceed to affirm, the <hi>mode and dreſs is directed</hi> in ſpecie, <hi>by the general rules of edification and order:</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rules for the guidance of mans wiſdome, have determined the ſpecial mode for miniſtration. Why may not ſome Son of the Church report on you, The Liturgie was <hi>enjoyned</hi> in ſpecie, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:35054:12"/>
14. 12, 26, 40. and <hi>endited in individuo</hi> by the Spirit as dictator, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 26. and be as ſoon believed, as you affirming it of concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Prayer? for theſe two are equally demonſtrable in the one, as in the other. And, Sir, let me tell you, <hi>non-ſence, tautologie, rude indigeſted expreſſions</hi> in conceived prayer, is an <hi>evil,</hi> a <hi>poſitive evil,</hi> as well as the order and method of Common-prayer; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are as cogent to exclude the <hi>injunction</hi> and <hi>enditement of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Do what you can, you moſt and will find, the <hi>Miniſterial mode</hi> is and muſt be <hi>humane,</hi> ſubject to humane weakneſs (which is a poſitive evil) in miniſtration; and Gods Worſhip muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and thereby exiſt betwixt God and his Church; yet this poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive evil is not <hi>fathered on the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your next Paragraph offereth an Anſwer to my Objection, <q>Our firſt Reformers, and <hi>Marian</hi> Martyrs, rejoyced and died under <note place="margin">Pag. 20.</note> a mode of Worſhip by which God could not be worſhipped. </q>Your Anſwer is five-fold.</p>
            <p>Your firſt Anſwer, by way of conceſſion, tells us, <q>This was the dark ſide of thoſe pillars; they were fallible men; <hi>Peter</hi> might <hi>Judaize;</hi> therefore we muſt meaſure truth by rule, and not by their practice.</q> Sir, you might have obſerved, their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice was not propounded as a pattern, but a proof; that though they <hi>miſſed it in the Miniſterial mode,</hi> yet God was <hi>worſhipped by them,</hi> in and by this mode. Sir, God did not leave them in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to him with <hi>adulterate worſhip,</hi> whileſt they witneſſed his truth. But, indeed, you obſerve not the purpoſe, ſcope, and ſtrength of any one Objection. The Martyrs abhorred the notion of <hi>being ſaved onely by true Doctrine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> which they were charged to believe. Would you have us believe they went to Heaven, who witneſſed true Doctrine, but worſhipped God with <hi>falſe Worſhip, will-worſhip,</hi> the <hi>worſhip adminiſtred and adminiſtrable by the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your ſecond Anſwer doth deny matter of fact, <q>That theſe Martyrs rejoyced in, and died for the Liturgie;</q> as if Life and Liturgie came in competition, you freely deny. You may, Sir, deny the Sun doth ſhine. This man is ſure well<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> read in our Book of Martyrs. Did not <hi>Cranmer, Ridley,</hi> and others, joyfully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Liturgie? Did not all that that then feared God in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> rejoyce at the eſtabliſhment of the Liturgie by the <hi>Statute of King</hi> Edw. 6. Did not <hi>Philpot</hi> appear in its defence at the <hi>Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation?</hi> Did not old <hi>Latimer</hi> juſtifie it in his <hi>Diſputation at</hi> Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford?
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35054:13"/>
Did not <hi>Rogers</hi> our Proto-martyr approve it, in his <hi>Speech</hi> digeſted to declare to the Commiſſioners who condemned him? Did not all that then ſuffered <hi>miniſter their laſt publick and dying de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions</hi> by the Liturgie? Did not the Congregations (who then neceſſarily ſerved God in corners) worſhip by the Liturgie? Did not they wiſh and wait for the return of the Liturgie, and rejoyce in its revival by <hi>Elizabeth?</hi> Came not <hi>Life and Liturgie in compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition,</hi> when the Articles objected againſt, and on which <hi>Thomas Watts, Thomas Osmond, Derrick Carver, John Launder,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rough</hi> the Miniſter, and <hi>Cuthbert Sympſon, Deacon of the congregation in</hi> Bowe-<hi>Church-yard,</hi> were condemned, was, that <hi>they uſed, attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, loved, laboured to reſtore the Engliſh Service, or Liturgie?</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded not good Mr. <hi>Bradford,</hi> They <hi>fell under Gods curſe for calling good evil, and evil good, who condemned the Engliſh Service of Hereſie?</hi> How far ſhort is he who concludeth, and confidently affirmeth the <hi>worſhip adminiſtred or adminiſtrable by the Liturgie, is not Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but</hi> cultus adulterinus? <hi>God is not worſhipped by the Liturgie.</hi> Sir, turn over the Book of Martyrs, you may run and read theſe demonſtrations of the matter of fact; it cannot be denied: Yet I tell the Zealots for the Liturgie, they inferr more upon this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, then theſe premiſſes will allow; for whilſt I am forced to produce them againſt this moſt rigid Separatiſt, to prove God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped by the Liturgie; I do deny their practice to be any way cogent, to confine all, or any miniſtration of Gods worſhip to this mode and Liturgie.</p>
            <p>Your third Anſwer, of the diſparity between their caſe and ours, hath been fully anſwered by Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> and me; who hath told you, the difference is <hi>gradual,</hi> not <hi>real;</hi> the worſhip of God was, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reformat.</hi> not <hi>Separ.</hi> p. 44, 45.</note> is, and muſt be always one and the ſame, though the Miniſterial mode do, and ought to vary.</p>
            <p>Your fourth Anſwer, <hi>ad hominem,</hi> is indeed moſt judicious; I affirm, <q>Miniſters may not lawfully miniſter by the Liturgie; therefore all that did, or do hereby miniſter, do miniſter by a ſinfull and unlawfull Form of Worſhip, a formal poſitive evil. I</q> did, I do ſo affirm; what then? I did not affirm, <q>The Worſhip adminiſtred, or adminiſtrable by this finfull mode, was not Gods Worſhip, or <hi>cultus adulterinus;</hi> or that God was not worſhipped by the <hi>Liturgie.</hi>
               </q> But I affirm the contrary.</p>
            <p>I did alſo affirm this <hi>evil, formal poſitive evil,</hi> to be a <hi>perſonal evil,</hi> conſiſtent with, whileſt converſant about Gods true worſhip, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35054:13"/>
therefore no ground of ſeparation; I affirmed <hi>ſalvability</hi> under this <hi>evil, poſitive evil.</hi> And herein your Cenſure is a manifeſt breach of Charity; you conclude the <hi>Martyrs had not Gods worſhip,</hi> but <hi>adulterate falſe worſhip;</hi> which is inconſiſtent with ſalvation; for otherwiſe, the very Devils may dance in hope of Heaven; for they <hi>believe</hi> and <hi>tremble,</hi> yea, and profeſs <hi>true Doctrine:</hi> I charge a defect in <hi>circumſtantials;</hi> you in the <hi>ſubject</hi> and <hi>ſubſtance:</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove a ſin of <hi>weakneſs,</hi> conſiſtent with ſalvation; you the <hi>heighth of wickedneſs, adulterate worſhip,</hi> which concludeth its ſubjects, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and dying (as you cannot deny the Martyrs to have done, if your Notion be true) under it, in utter impoſſibility of ſalvation: Have you not cauſe to ſing, <hi>jam ſumus ergo pares?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your fifth Anſwer is, <hi>The Martyrs devotion was not confined to the Liturgie.</hi> Nor is theirs who uſe it, and adminiſter by it; or ours who attend the ſame.</p>
            <p>Your third Propoſition reſolving this firſt Query concerning <note place="margin">Pag. 21.</note> the <hi>expulſion of the Liturgie,</hi> I paſs, as not concerned in it; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to your Concluſion, though grieved to ſee you give ſo much advantage to <hi>Liturgical Zealots,</hi> as by your weakneſs and wildneſs of Argumentation you have done: I ſay, it ought not to be; but being, will not warrant a ſeparation.</p>
            <p>The Objections you take from me, I will obſerve your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to.</p>
            <p>The firſt is Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi>'s <hi>ſence of ſcandal.</hi> Your Anſwer doth witneſs, you either did not read, or did not regard and conſider Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Plea to the Barr of <hi>Scandal;</hi> you would elſe have ſeen his care of, and <hi>compaſſion to the weak;</hi> his <hi>conceſſion of ſcandal</hi> in all acts of <hi>liberty, &amp; ſui juris;</hi> and his neglect of ſcandal onely when it doth obviate his <hi>duty.</hi> But you inſult here, as every where, on manifeſt miſtake, wonder at the charge whileſt you will.</p>
            <p>Your fifth Propoſition is your Concluſion, built on the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noted horrible and erroneous premiſes, and muſt be conſonant <note place="margin">Pa. 26, 27.</note> thereunto; I will to it ſay no more: but I deny the Concluſion.</p>
            <p>Your ſecond Query, as a ſpecies of the firſt, is of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <note place="margin">Quaer. 2.</note> and in it included, diſcuſſed, and reſolved; yet you do particularly ſtate it thus: <hi>What is that which may warrant and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit from Schiſm, a perſons non-communion with the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, under the preſent mode, manner, and method of adminiſtration?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:35054:14"/>
In this Query, I cannot but note, that the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> as in the former <hi>worſhip,</hi> abſtracted from the <hi>Miniſterial mode,</hi> is propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as the Object of non-communion.</p>
            <p>Your Anſwer to this Query is general, and granted you in <hi>Theſi; That if one cannot communicate in the Lords Supper without ſin, he is warranted in his non-communion:</hi> But your <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption is yet denied. Nor can your horrid breach of Charity paſs without obſervation, <hi>That the mode, manner, and method of adminiſtration, maketh the Lords Supper poyſon:</hi> whereby you muſt conclude, that all who have, all who do communicate in this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, thus miniſtred, have received <hi>poyſon:</hi> Yet you give us no proof for this <hi>Martyr-blaſpheming,</hi> Saint-damning Notion. But you pretend to anſwer ſome of mine Objections.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>What ſuperſtitions and corruptions attend the Miniſtration of the Lords Supper, in which he muſt perſonally act, ſo as to become guilty of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Object. pag. 98.</note> 
               <hi>the ſame?</hi> You anſwer, Two, the <hi>Service,</hi> and the <hi>Geſture; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer</hi> and <hi>kneeling.</hi> But, Sir, you have not proved the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants perſonal acting in Common-prayer;</hi> nor <hi>an impoſſibility of receiving the Lords Supper without this geſture:</hi> Suppoſe theſe war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable reaſons, your ſeceſſion cannot be warranted by them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til you have eſſayed all means for publick communion without them; in which, I am ſure, you might have found a <hi>poſſibility of enjoying</hi> this, with at leaſt connivance as to thoſe Ceremonies which call for perſonal action.</p>
            <p>Your Plea, that the geſture of <hi>kneeling</hi> is <hi>impoſed,</hi> is meerly fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous; King <hi>James</hi> his Proclamation was <hi>no Law;</hi> the Statute of 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. extendeth not to Succeſſors; but if it do, his now Majeſties Declaration concerning Eccleſiaſtical affairs, hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged the Canon challenging this Authority; the Common-Prayer Book doth <hi>imply,</hi> and <hi>ſuppoſe,</hi> not <hi>impoſe this geſture:</hi> your reaſon is as weak in matters of <hi>Law,</hi> as of <hi>Divinity.</hi> And, Sir, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal acting in the Service and Miniſtration, being as it may be avoided, it will be an hard diſpute, whether the <hi>Geſture impoſed</hi> will conſtitute a <hi>ſufficient Barr</hi> to ſo great Priviledge, and ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Duty: But that it maketh the Lords Supper <hi>poyſon,</hi> expreſs <hi>poyſon,</hi> is out of diſpute to men of modeſty and charity, who dare not conclude all in Hell, who have received, and do receive the Elements <hi>kneeling.</hi> I am, Sir, no Advocate for this Geſture; but I abominate your venemous Notion. <note place="margin">Object. 2. pag. 30.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Your ſecond Objection is <hi>ad hominem</hi> thus; <hi>Corruptions in point
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35054:14"/>
of geſture, are to Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>a warrantable ground of non-communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But, corruptions in point of geſture are corruptions extrinſecal and circumſtantial;</hi> Ergo, <hi>Some corruptions extrinſecal and circumſtantial, at a warrantable ground for non-communion.</hi> I pray you, Sir, when, and where did Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſay, <hi>Corruptions in point of geſture is a warrantable ground for non-communion?</hi> I find it not in any of his writings: I ſay indeed, <hi>Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>put by communion becauſe of the Geſture, which is his perſonal act, and he judgeth ſinfull, is barred, by violence driven, he doth not go:</hi> This, Sir, is not repugnant to what I ſaid, <hi>The worſhip attended with circumſtantial corruptions, may with ſafety, and muſt in duty be uſed;</hi> for, Sir, every <hi>ſinfull act, perſonally done,</hi> becometh a <hi>ſubſtantial corruption;</hi> but <hi>done by others onely,</hi> and about Gods worſhip, it is <hi>circumſtantial,</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecal,</hi> and becometh not my Guilt. Again, Sir, your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>a fortiori,</hi> hath the little force of your whole Argumentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>If corruption in point of geſture be a warrantable ground for non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communion</hi> (which you falſly ſay is confeſſed) <hi>then much more the Liturgie:</hi> Sir, here is a meer <hi>non ſequitur;</hi> for the <hi>geſture</hi> (if ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) is the <hi>perſonal act</hi> of the Communicant, who is wholly <hi>mute,</hi> and <hi>paſſive,</hi> in the Liturgical miniſtration, in which he needeth not to act at all.</p>
            <p>Your third Querie is in effect the ſame with the firſt and ſecond, concerning the Communion in the Service or Worſhip exhibited by the Liturgie. In the reſolution of which, you run round, like the Horſe in his Mill; and whileſt I grant you the Liturgie is an <hi>evil conſtitution,</hi> as it is a <hi>Miniſterial mode<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> you fly upon the <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip miniſtred and miniſtrable by it;</hi> and tell us, <hi>The worſhip mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by the Liturgie is not performable by faith;</hi> the <hi>worſhip is ſinful;</hi> the <hi>worſhip is unlawfull:</hi> to theſe I ſhall ſay nothing more then what I have ſaid before; If this Worſhip miniſtred (be the miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what it will) be <hi>cultus adulterinus, ſinfull worſhip, unlawfull worſhip,</hi> God hath no ſtated publick worſhip in the world; for <hi>Word, Prayer, and, Sacraments</hi> are the worſhip. In your laſt, <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie</hi> was the object of your Communion; but in this, <hi>worſhip, diſtinct from, and oppoſed to Liturgie,</hi> is the object of your non-Communion; that we may know <hi>God is not worſhipped by the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie,</hi> you ſpeak out, the <hi>worſhip is ſinfull,</hi> not <hi>Gods worſhip,</hi> not <hi>performable in faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having diſcourſed at Rovers concerning the ſubject, <hi>worſhip,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag 34.</note> you come to the Predicate, <hi>miniſtred by the Liturgie;</hi> and ſtate my
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35054:15"/>
Objection; <hi>The Liturgie is onely a Miniſterial mode, which the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are not to be Judges in; and therefore all the guilt reſulting from thence is perſonal,</hi> i. e. <hi>peculiar to the Miniſter.</hi> To this you gravely anſwer, <hi>This twenty-year-old Notion is become an Article of Mr.</hi> Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons <hi>Creed;</hi> and in your Margin you referr to Mr. <hi>John Ball.</hi> Is age any harm to the Notion? Is it the worſe for being ſtated by Learned, Judicious <hi>John Ball?</hi> No, Sir; theſe add force and luſtre to it, and acquit Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> from novelty and ſingularity in this notion; your notions are not two years old, nor can they claim any other Author, ſave acute <hi>T. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, You deny <hi>the Liturgie is any Miniſtrial mode, more then the Book of Scripture is in the Miniſters reading.</hi> If ſo much, Sir, <note place="margin">Pag. 34.</note> is not that enough? That Gods Word be read in ſuch a <hi>Tranſlation, meaſure,</hi> and <hi>order,</hi> is the miniſtration humane? And that Prayer be pronounced in ſuch <hi>method, order,</hi> and <hi>expreſſions,</hi> ſtated, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately conceived, is the <hi>humane miniſtration thereof;</hi> edifying <hi>expreſſions,</hi> and reverential <hi>manner of delivery,</hi> you grant, is the <hi>Miniſterial mode;</hi> theſe may be both exhibited by a ſtinted Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie: But, Sir, doth the Liturgie (whatever be its order) do any thing more then <hi>exhibite Word, Prayer, and Sacraments,</hi> in ſuch an humane mode and dreſs between God and his People? and is not this the <hi>formalis ratio</hi> of miniſtration of Gods worſhip, to which edification and order are ſeparable Adjuncts? Is yet the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie <hi>no Miniſterial mode?</hi> Is Prayer read, no Prayer? and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments miniſtred by preſcribed forms, no Sacraments? Is ſuch mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, no miniſtration? Will you ſay it, and ſtand to it? I may commend (or rather condemn) your confidence: You ſay, The <hi>Popiſh Miſſal</hi> may be termed a <hi>Miniſterial mode:</hi> It may ſo, it <note place="margin">Pag. 35.</note> is ſo; yet it may not be attended by the people, becauſe the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter miniſtred by this Miniſterial mode,</hi> is either <hi>no worſhip, or falſe worſhip:</hi> Your parallel between the <hi>Popiſh Miſſal</hi> and <hi>Liturgie,</hi> is very ſquare; they are both a <hi>Miniſterial mode;</hi> in the Popiſh Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, the <hi>ſubject matter,</hi> the <hi>worſhip,</hi> is vitiated; in the Liturgie, the <hi>ſubject matter,</hi> the <hi>worſhip,</hi> is right and good, but the <hi>miniſtration</hi> and <hi>mode</hi> is bad; A full agreement! an excellent Harp and Harrow! The Popiſh communicants contract guilt by communion in <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous, ſuperſtitious worſhip,</hi> miniſtred by their <hi>Prieſts and Miſſal; Ergo,</hi> Our people contract guilt by communicating in Gods <hi>true</hi> and <hi>own worſhip</hi> miniſtred by the Liturgie: Rare Reaſon! but I muſt remember, the worſhip is <hi>cultus adulterinus,</hi> and the Liturgie is not a <hi>Miniſterial mode.</hi> But</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:35054:15"/>
Who is this that crieth out, that is a dangerous Principle, That <hi>people may lawfully communicate by that form, mode, and order of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which a Miniſter cannot lawfully adminiſter by?</hi> D. G. <hi>redivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus?</hi> This quarrel is proper for a <hi>Liturgical Conſiderator.</hi> But <note place="margin">Pag. 35.</note> wherein lieth the danger of this Principle? <hi>Such Opiniators fondly try an experiment, how near they may approach to ſin without ſin.</hi> How, Sir? Is diſtribution of different capacities of Miniſter &amp; People, and determination of the proper Duties of each, a fond experiment? Is an approach to ſin, without ſin, ſo greatly dangerous, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the critical, neceſſarily caſuiſtical part of Divinity? Is a ſerious conſideration of a Caſe of Conſcience, the wanton act of the wild School-men? Will not an Act of Parliament, a penal Law, clear this dangerous Principle, and make you, and many your Proſelytes, make this near approach to ſin without ſin? Doth not the Law, publick Peace, and Order, with Self-preſervation, conclude the man under ſin, whoſe condeſcenſions came not near to ſin, without ſin? If we ſcape the ſin, ſhall we not bleſs God, and do any thing with comfort? But<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Your third Anſwer is; The people have <hi>Judicium diſcretionis,</hi> you grant, <hi>not of Order and Method,</hi> to <hi>direct and determine that;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 36.</note> 
               <hi>this is proper to the Miniſter.</hi> We are, Sir, in this agreed; but your fancy doth confound the <hi>medium cultus</hi> with the <hi>modus miniſterialis;</hi> the laſt you will not allow, and the firſt you do not underſtand; there is the reaſon of the ſtrife: I pray you, Sir, ſtudy the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of theſe terms in reference to Gods Worſhip; for want of this, you miſ-apply <hi>Zanchy</hi> and all other Authors.</p>
            <p>Another Objection: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder this Miniſterial mode the people are purely paſſive.</hi> You anſwer by way of Queſtion, <hi>In what worſhip are the people active, if not in the worſhip in queſtion, who cannot deny their</hi> Amen <hi>to any petition in the Common-Prayer?</hi> Who, Sir, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth the peoples acting in the Worſhip? The Miniſterial mode (which I muſt and will retain) is the matter in queſtion: You muſt prove, That the <hi>Miniſterial mode is the Object of the Peoples Amen.</hi> Your ſuppoſition doth not evade mine alluſion to the <hi>Speaker</hi> or <hi>Recorder;</hi> unleſs you make it certain, that the <hi>order and terms of their Speech</hi> is determined by the King, and ſo their Office be deſtroyed, and reduced to the Act common to every Boy. In the Caſe of <hi>Elies</hi> ſons, you grant, the <hi>people who loathed did not leave the offerings of the Lord:</hi> Nor do you urge any Reaſon cogent to them, which in its general nature is not cogent to us; we have
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35054:16"/>
               <hi>true worſhip,</hi> and a <hi>lawfull,</hi> though not <hi>Levitical Miniſtry:</hi> The force and pertinency of this inſtance, as alſo that of the high places, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jerub. juſt.</hi> p. 29, 30.</note> is fully urged in my laſt; I ſhall onely leave you to review it, and ſee what you now object is fully anſwered.</p>
            <p>Your Notion of <hi>civil preſence,</hi> urged in your fourth Queſtion, is ſo notorious to guard your <hi>attendance on a Maſs, Alchoran, or ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 39, 40, 41.</note> 
               <hi>worſhip;</hi> ſo repugnant to the <hi>principle</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Fathers, and Martyrs, that all ſober Chriſtians will ſee it a fancy, and conclude you will never make a Martyr. I ſhall not therefore ſtand to dilate upon it; onely deſire you to tell us in your next, what it is ſhall predicate Civil preſence? in what lieth the <hi>ratio formalis</hi> thereof? whereby we may difference it from Religious preſence? Do you predicate it, <hi>Civil preſence</hi> ratione <hi>ſubjecti,</hi> becauſe the perſon preſent is a <hi>civil perſon?</hi> If ſo, Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical perſons will be at a loſs, and your ſelf not defended. Do you predicate it <hi>Civil preſence</hi> ratione <hi>objecti,</hi> the buſineſs at which we are preſent is civil buſineſs? that will not warrant a preſence at Common-Prayer, for that is <hi>Religious</hi> (though in your fancy falſe Religion) <hi>buſineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do you, as you ſeem to do, predicate it <hi>Civil preſence,</hi> from the reaſon which doth enforce it, the <hi>Law of a Civil Magiſtrate?</hi> then preſence at Maſs, at a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Alchoran, or Idolatrous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice will be <hi>civil preſence;</hi> for in all theſe my <hi>body,</hi> the <hi>ſuppoſitum,</hi> is at the Magiſtrates command. Nor will your ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> contradicting notion, That the <hi>Common-Prayer is not Heatheniſh, or Popiſh Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> any thing relieve you, whileſt the <hi>worſhip adminiſtred and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrable</hi> by the Liturgie is <hi>cultus adulterinus,</hi> and as <hi>prayer before an Image,</hi> as is before obſerved. Then our primitive Martyrs were <hi>Felones de ſe,</hi> who were deſtroyed for not yielding their preſence at Idol ſacrifices on the Edicts of the Emperour. Until we know what is a <hi>civil preſence,</hi> we muſt admire the largeneſs of your fancy, under the great ſtrictneſs of your Conſcience: and be ſure you can foot it any way to free your ſelf from danger; for your <hi>neceſſitas offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cii</hi> doth fail, when the Magiſtrate doth <hi>Religiouſly</hi> (in zeal, whether good or bad, I will not diſpute) compel your <hi>perſonal attendance</hi> on a <hi>Religious adminiſtration,</hi> by you judged <hi>cultus adulterinus:</hi> Nor will your <hi>neceſſitas beneficii</hi> hold againſt that Rule, <hi>We muſt not do evil that good may come thereby:</hi> It cannot pleaſe me, that any called a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> ſhould own and argue the Jeſuitical partition of <hi>body</hi> and <hi>ſoul,</hi> in external communion with the Church viſible, in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35054:16"/>
outward Ordinances; in which, the <hi>quale of my preſence</hi> muſt be judged by its appearance <hi>ad vulgus</hi> to the obſerving world, and not by mine <hi>inward intention,</hi> and <hi>mental reſervation: Pudeat nobis haec dici potuiſſe</hi>—Know you not, that all Proteſtants have abandoned, abominated, and exploded this diſtinction, as the odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous covert of <hi>Church-Papiſts,</hi> in their Hypocritical obedience to the Statutes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>, which commanded their preſence at Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice?</p>
            <p>Your laſt Quaery, concerning the Solemn League and Covenant, is by your ſelf reſolved, without any regard, or the leaſt Anſwer to the three Conſiderations I have laid before you in my laſt: I will not therefore ſtrive to word it with you to no purpoſe; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, and rationally contradict what hath been ſaid; otherwiſe, you multiply words in vain. In all you have now ſaid on this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, you have ſaid no <hi>new thing;</hi> therefore I will ſay <hi>nothing;</hi> but pray that God may break the Snares with which you are entangled, and give you unfeigned Repentance.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
